Guide to the George B. McClellan, Jr. Scrapbooks 1860s-1909 (bulk 1904-1909) MS 3187
New-York Historical Society
George B. McClellan, Jr. scrapbooks
1860s-1909 (bulk 1904-1909)
New-York Historical Society
McClellan, George B. (George Brinton), 1865-1940
MS 3187
38.5 Linear feet in 26 boxes (89 volumes)
The collection includes 89 volumes, mostly scrapbooks containing newspaper clippings tracing George B. McClellan, Jr.'s (1865-1940) tenure as mayor of New York City from 1904 to 1909. Six volumes include copies of McClellan's mayoral speeches, his veto statements, outgoing letters, budgets, incoming reports, and other documents. Six scrapbooks include clippings from his political career before becoming mayor. Three scrapbooks relate to McClellan's father, George B. McClellan (1826-1885), the Civil War general of the same name, mostly concerning his death and memorials.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers. Materials are stored offsite and advance notice is required for use. Please contact manuscripts@nyhistory.org prior to your research visit to coordinate access. Keep in mind that it will take between two (2) and five (5) business days for collections to arrive, and you should plan your research accordingly.
Scope and Contents
The bulk of the collection is comprised of scrapbooks dating from 1904-09, the years of McClellan's tenure as New York City mayor. Most of these scrapbooks hold only newspaper clippings and are in their original arrangement, which is broadly topical. These topics are "political," (22 volumes), "editorial: political & department," (9 volumes), "department" (28 volumes), "legislature," (5 volumes), and "political cartoons" (7 volumes). Political clippings are generally those that concern elections, party politics, candidates, and other partisan political matters. Department clippings relate to city agencies, bureaus, and other administrative and policy matters. Legislature clippings relate to New York state legislative concerns. The title of some albums refer to editorials, but these can be found in the other albums as well. The albums titled as cartoons hold those, but general clippings also. Each album is indexed and their clippings are captioned.
In addition to the clippings scrapbooks, there are 6 volumes of the "Mayor's Flimsey Books," so called likely because most of the documents in these albums are on fragile, tissue-like paper. These documents include copies of typed speeches, outgoing letters, incoming reports, mayoral veto statements, budgets, appointments, and other important documents tracing McClellan's mayoralty and political positions. Rapid transit, city governance, and street gas lighting are among the many topics reflected in the flimsies. The flimsey albums are indexed and the documents captioned.
Also related to McClellan's mayoralty is a bound volume of the published Supplement to the City Record of July 1909, with a comprehensive list of city officials and employees, and a scrapbook of lists and other arrangements for the ceremonies of the opening of the Willamsburg Bridge in 1903, which included mayor-elect McClellan.
The collection also includes 6 volumes of clippings documenting McClellan's career from 1890-1903, that is, before he became mayor, and one volume of reviews of his 1904 book "The Oligarchy of Venice."
Finally, the collection includes 3 volumes of clippings concerning McClellan's father, the Civil War general of the same name. Some of these clippings date from the 1860s, but most seem to date from around the elder McClellan's death in 1885 and later.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Georgiana McClellan (Mrs. George Brinton McClellan), June 5, 1942, and May 5, 1943.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged with the scrapbooks from McClellan's mayoralty, which comprise the bulk of the collection, preceding those related to the years prior to his mayoralty, followed by the few scrapbooks related to McClellan's father, the Civil War general. McClellan mayoralty scrapbooks retain their original thematic and chronological arrangement.
Each album was given a unique identifier (e.g., SN-1, SN-2) by the processing archivists. These are intended only to facilitate reference and are not indicative of any overall numbering scheme found in the collection itself.
Biographical / Historical
George Brinton McClellan (1865-1940) was the son of the Civil War general of the same name. McClellan served as President of New York City's Board of Aldermen (1892-1894) and later for eight years in the U.S. Congress (1895-1903). He was Mayor of New York City from 1904-1909, which is the period that most of these scrapbooks are focused on. After leaving office, McClellan went on to his alma mater, Princeton University, where he lectured in public affairs and economic history. He married Georgiana Heckscher, the donor of the collection, in 1889.
(This note is based primarily on Eleanor J. Conway's article about many of the scrapbooks in N-YHS's Quarterly Bulletin of October 1942.)
Related Materials
N-YHS also holds the letterpress copybooks maintained by McClellan during his New York City mayoralty. These were also donated by Georgiana McClellan in May 1943, but cataloged separately at some point. Call phrase: BV McClellan.
Other documents related to McClellan can also be found with a search on his name in Bobcat, the online catalog.
Mayors -- New York (State) -- New York.; Speeches, addresses, etc., American -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government.; Scrapbooks.; Newspaper clippings.; McClellan, George B. (George Brinton), 1826-1885
- Political clippings, 1904 May-September (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN-1)
- Political clippings, 1904 September-October (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN-2)
- Political clippings, 1904 October-December (Offsite-box 1, Volume SN-3)
- Political clippings, 1905 January-September (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-4)
- Political clippings, 1905 September-October (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-5)
- Political clippings, 1905 October (Offsite-box 2, Volume SN-6)
- Political clippings, 1905 October-November (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN-7)
- Political clippings, 1905 November-December (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN-8)
- Political clippings, 1905 December (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN-9)
- Political clippings, 1906 January-May (Offsite-box 3, Volume SN-10)
- Political clippings, 1906 May-September (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN-11)
- Political clippings, 1906 September-October (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN-12)
- Political clippings, 1906 October (Offsite-box 4, Volume SN-13)
- Political clippings, 1906 October-December (Offsite-box 5, Volume SN-14)
- Political clippings, 1907 January-June (Offsite-box 5, Volume SN-15)
- Political clippings, 1907 June-October (Offsite-box 5, Volume SN-16)
- Political clippings, 1907 November-1908 May (Offsite-box 6, Volume SN-17)
- Political clippings, 1908 June-October (Offsite-box 6, Volume SN-!8)
- Political clippings, 1908 November-December (Offsite-box 6, Volume SN-19)
- Political clippings, 1909 January-October (Offsite-box 7, Volume SN-20)
- Political clippings, 1909 October (Offsite-box 7, Volume SN-21)
- Political clippings, 1909 October-December (Offsite-box 7, Volume SN-22)
- Mayor's Flimsey Book, 1904 January-1905 April (Offsite-box 8, Volume SN-23)
  Scope and Contents
  This volume includes, among other topics, expressions of condolence received concerning the General Slocum disaster.
- Mayor's Flimsey Book, 1905 April-December (Offsite-box 8, Volume SN-24)
  This volume includes, among other topics, speeches on the occasion of the opening of the Staten Island ferry and the 250th anniversary of the arrival of Jews in America.
- Mayor's Flimsey Book, 1905 December-1907 October (Offsite-box 8, Volume SN-25)
  This volume includes, among other topics, lists of contributors to a relief fund formed in New York in response to the San Francisco 1906 earthquake.
- Mayor's Flimsey Book, 1907 October-1908 September (Offsite-box 8, Volume SN-26)
- Mayor's Flimsey Book, 1908 October-1909 May (Offsite-box 8, Volume SN-27)
- Mayor's Flimsey Book, 1909 May-December (Offsite-box 9, Volume SN-28)
- Editorials. Political & Department clippings, 1906 August-October (Offsite-box 9, Volume SN-29)
- Editorials. Political & Department clippings, 1906 October-1907 January (Offsite-box 9, Volume SN-30)
- Editorials. Political & Department clippings, 1907 February-June (Offsite-box 10, Volume SN-31)
- Editorials. Political & Department clippings, 1907 June-December (Offsite-box 10, Volume SN-32)
- Editorials. Political & Department clippings, 1908 January-June (Offsite-box 10, Volume SN-33)
- Editorials. Political & Department clippings, 1908 July-December (Offsite-box 11, Volume SN-34)
- Editorials. Political & Department clippings, 1909 January-May (Offsite-box 11, Volume SN-35)
- Editorials. Political & Department clippings, 1909 June-October (Offsite-box 11, Volume SN-36)
- Editorials. Political & Department clippings, 1909 October-December (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-37)
- Legislature clippings, 1904 March-May (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-38)
- Legislature clippings, 1905 January-June (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-39)
- Legislature clippings, 1906 January-June (Offsite-box 12, Volume SN-40)
- Legislature clippings, 1907 January-September (Offsite-box 13, Volume SN-41)
- Legislature clippings, 1908 (Offsite-box 13, Volume SN-42)
- Department clippings, 1904 January-February (Offsite-box 13, Volume SN-43)
- Department clippings, 1904 February-April (Offsite-box 13, Volume SN-44)
- Department clippings, 1904 April-June (Offsite-box 14, Volume SN-45)
- Department clippings, 1904 July-November (Offsite-box 14, Volume SN-46)
- Department clippings, 1904 November-1905 January (Offsite-box 14, Volume SN-47)
- Department clippings, 1905 January-February (Offsite-box 14, Volume SN-48)
- Department clippings, 1905 March-July (Offsite-box 15, Volume SN-49)
- Department clippings, 1905 July-December (Offsite-box 15, Volume SN-50)
- Department clippings, 1905 December-1906 February (Offsite-box 15, Volume SN-51)
- Department clippings, 1906 February-May (Offsite-box 15, Volume SN-52)
- Department clippings, 1906 May-June (Offsite-box 16, Volume SN-53)
- Department clippings, 1906 July-December (Offsite-box 16, Volume SN-54)
- Department clippings, 1907 January-March (Offsite-box 16, Volume SN-55)
- Department clippings, 1907 March-June (Offsite-box 17, Volume SN-56)
- Department clippings, 1907 June-September (Offsite-box 17, Volume SN-57)
- Department clippings, 1907 September-November (Offsite-box 17, Volume SN-58)
- Department clippings, 1907 November-December (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN-59)
- Department clippings, 1908 January-February (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN-60)
- Department clippings, 1908 February-May (Offsite-box 18, Volume SN-61)
- Department clippings, 1908 May-August (Offsite-box 19, Volume SN-62)
- Department clippings, 1908 September-November (Offsite-box 19, Volume SN-63)
- Department clippings, 1908 November-December (Offsite-box 19, Volume SN-64)
- Department clippings, 1909 January-February (Offsite-box 20, Volume SN-65)
- Department clippings, 1909 February-April (Offsite-box 20, Volume SN-66)
- Department clippings, 1909 May-June (Offsite-box 20, Volume SN-67)
- Department clippings, 1909 June-September (Offsite-box 21, Volume SN-68)
- Department clippings, 1909 September-December (Offsite-box 21, Volume SN-69)
- Department clippings, 1909 December (Offsite-box 21, Volume SN-70)
- Political cartoon clippings, 1904 January-July (Offsite-box 22, Volume SN-71)
- Political cartoon clippings, 1904 August-1905 July (Offsite-box 22, Volume SN-72)
- Political cartoon clippings, 1905 July-December (Offsite-box 22, Volume SN-73)
- Political cartoon clippings, 1906 January-November (Offsite-box 23, Volume SN-74)
- Political cartoon clippings, 1906 November-1908 September (Offsite-box 23, Volume SN-75)
- Political cartoon clippings, 1908 October-1909 July (Offsite-box 23, Volume SN-76)
- Political cartoon clippings, 1909 August-December (Offsite-box 24, Volume SN-77)
- Detached spines, 1904-1909 (Offsite-box 24)
  Holds several spines that detached from some of the above volumes.
- Bound copy of City Record, Supplement, 1909 (Offsite-box 24, Volume SN-78)
  This volume holds the Supplement to the City Record of July 31, 1909, which is the comprehensive list of "Officials and employees of the departments, bureaus and offices of the City of New York and of the counties therein contained, from January 1 to June 30, 1909, inclusive."
- Programs & invitation lists, etc., 1903 (Offsite-box 24, Volume SN-79)
  Volume of documents related to arrangements for the ceremonies for the opening of the Williamsburg Bridge.
- Clippings previous to mayoralty, 1890-1894 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN-83)
- Clippings previous to mayoralty, 1895-1898 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN-84)
- Clippings previous to mayoralty, 1898-1899 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN-85)
- Clippings previous to mayoralty, 1899-1900 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN-86)
- Clippings previous to mayoralty, 1901-1902 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN-87)
- Clippings previous to mayoralty, 1902-1903 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN-88)
- "The Oligarchy of Venice" clippings, 1904 (Offsite-box 26, Volume SN-89)
- General George McClellan clippings, 1880s (Offsite-box 25, Volume SN-80)
  Spine of album embossed "Miss M. McC.'
- General George McClellan clippings, 1860s-1880s (Offsite-box 25, Volume SN-81)
  Spine of album embossed "Mrs. McC."
- General George McClellan clippings, 1860s-1900 (Offsite-box 25, Volume SN-82)